<PoCProjects><Project acronym="2-NanoSi"><Rcn>196369</Rcn><Nid>13899</Nid><HI>Fundacio Privada Institut Catala D'investigacio Quimica, Spain</HI><Name>Ratiometric FRET Based Nanosensors for Trypsin Related Human Recessive Diseases</Name><PI>Alice Jenkins</PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2014-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>The project aims to create a demo system for cost effective, non-invasive device for rapid detection of cystic fibrosis in humans.
The detection of human recessive diseases has been dominated by the use of fluorescent biomarkers, based on organic dyes, helping researchers to study and analyse gene expression, cell cycle, and enzymatic activity. Among several proteolytic enzymes, trypsin has attracted much attention, as it is a target in the study of various important human recessive diseases including, for example, cystic fibrosis (CF).
We present herein two colour encoded silica nanospheres (2nanoSi) for the fluorescence quantitative ratiometric determination of cystic in humans. Current detection technologies for cystic fibrosis diagnosis are slow, costly and suffer from false positives. The 2nanoSi proved to be a fast (minutes), a single-step and with two times higher sensitivity than the state-of-the-art biomarkers based sensors for cystic fibrosis, allowing the quantification of trypsin concentrations in a wide range (25-350 &#956;g/L). Moreover, our approach can be used from the 4th day of life when the trypsin concentration is already the same as in adults. Furthermore, as trypsin is directly related to the development of cystic fibrosis (CF), different human phenotypes, i.e. normal (160-340 &#956;g/L), CF homozygotic (0-90 &#956;g/L), and CF heterozygotic (91-349 &#956;g/L), respectively, can be determined using our 2nanoSi nanospheres. We anticipate the 2nanoSi system to be a starting point for non-invasive, easy-to-use and cost effective ratiometric fluorescence biomarker for recessive genetic diseases alike human cystic fibrosis.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>150,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2015-04-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2016-03-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2D-CHEM"><Rcn>204139</Rcn><Nid>16076</Nid><HI>Univerzita Palackeho V Olomouci, Czech Republic</HI><Name>Two-Dimensional Chemistry towards New Graphene Derivatives</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), ERC-2015-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>The suite of graphene&#8217;s unique properties and applications can be enormously enhanced by its functionalization. As non-covalently functionalized graphenes do not target all graphene&#8217;s properties and may suffer from limited stability, covalent functionalization represents a promising way for controlling graphene&#8217;s properties. To date, only a few well-defined graphene derivatives have been introduced. Among them, fluorographene (FG) stands out as a prominent member because of its easy synthesis and high stability. Being a perfluorinated hydrocarbon, FG was believed to be as unreactive as the two-dimensional counterpart perfluoropolyethylene (Teflon&#174;). However, our recent experiments showed that FG is not chemically inert and can be used as a viable precursor for synthesizing graphene derivatives. This surprising behavior indicates that common textbook grade knowledge cannot blindly be applied to the chemistry of 2D materials. Further, there might be specific rules behind the chemistry of 2D materials, forming a new chemical discipline we tentatively call 2D chemistry. The main aim of the project is to explore, identify and apply the rules of 2D chemistry starting from FG. Using the knowledge gained of 2D chemistry, we will attempt to control the chemistry of various 2D materials aimed at preparing stable graphene derivatives with designed properties, e.g., 1-3 eV band gap, fluorescent properties, sustainable magnetic ordering and dispersability in polar media. The new graphene derivatives will be applied in sensing, imaging, magnetic delivery and catalysis and new emerging applications arising from the synergistic phenomena are expected. We envisage that new applications will be opened up that benefit from the 2D scaffold and tailored properties of the synthesized derivatives. The derivatives will be used for the synthesis of 3D hybrid materials by covalent linking of the 2D sheets joined with other organic and inorganic molecules, nanomaterials or biomacromolecules.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,831,103</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2016-06-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2021-05-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="3D Reloaded"><Rcn>196582</Rcn><Nid>13774</Nid><HI>Technische Universitaet Muenchen, Germany</HI><Name>3D Reloaded: Novel Algorithms for 3D Shape Inference and Analysis</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), ERC-2014-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>Despite their amazing success, we believe that computer vision algorithms have only scratched the surface of what can be done in terms of modeling and understanding our world from images. We believe that novel image analysis techniques will be a major enabler and driving force behind next-generation technologies, enhancing everyday life and opening up radically new possibilities. And we believe that the key to achieving this is to develop algorithms for reconstructing and analyzing the 3D structure of our world. 

In this project, we will focus on three lines of research:

A) We will develop algorithms for 3D reconstruction from standard color cameras and from RGB-D cameras. In particular, we will promote real-time-capable direct and dense methods. In contrast to the classical two-stage approach of sparse feature-point based motion estimation and subsequent dense reconstruction, these methods optimally exploit all color information to jointly estimate dense geometry and camera motion.

B) We will develop algorithms for 3D shape analysis, including rigid and non-rigid matching, decomposition and interpretation of 3D shapes. We will focus on algorithms which are optimal or near-optimal. One of the major computational challenges lies in generalizing existing 2D shape analysis techniques to shapes in 3D and 4D (temporal evolutions of 3D shape).

C) We will develop shape priors for 3D reconstruction. These can be learned from sample shapes or acquired during the reconstruction process. For example, when reconstructing a larger office algorithms may exploit the geometric self-similarity of the scene, storing a model of a chair and its multiple instances only once rather than multiple times. 

Advancing the state of the art in geometric reconstruction and geometric analysis will have a profound impact well beyond computer vision. We strongly believe that we have the necessary competence to pursue this project. Preliminary results have been well received by the community.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>2,000,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2015-09-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2020-08-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="3D-JOINT"><Rcn>197262</Rcn><Nid>14340</Nid><HI>Universitair Medisch Centrum Utrecht, Netherlands</HI><Name>3D Bioprinting of JOINT Replacements</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), ERC-2014-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>The world has a significant medical challenge in repairing injured or diseased joints. Joint degeneration and its related pain is a major socio-economic burden that will increase over the next decade and is currently addressed by implanting a metal prosthesis. For the long term, the ideal solution to joint injury is to successfully regenerate rather than replace the damaged cartilage with synthetic implants. Recent advances in key technologies are now bringing this &#8220;holy grail&#8221; within reach; regenerative approaches, based on cell therapy, are already clinically available albeit only for smaller focal cartilage defects.
One of these key technologies is three-dimensional (3D) bio-printing, which provides a greatly controlled placement and organization of living constructs through the layer-by-layer deposition of materials and cells. These tissue constructs can be applied as tissue models for research and screening. However, the lack of biomechanical properties of these tissue constructs has hampered their application to the regeneration of damaged, degenerated or diseased tissue.

Having established a cartilage-focussed research laboratory in the University Medical Center Utrecht, I have addressed this biomechanical limitation of hydrogels through the use of hydrogel composites. Specifically, I have pioneered a 3D bio-printing technology that combines accurately printed small diameter thermoplast filaments with cell invasive hydrogels to form strong fibre-reinforced constructs. This, in combination with bioreactor technology, is the key to the generation of larger, complex tissue constructs with cartilage-like biomechanical resilience. With 3D-JOINT I will use my in-depth bio-printing and bioreactor knowledge and experience to develop a multi-phasic 3D-printed biological replacement of the joint.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,998,871</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2015-07-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2020-06-30</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="3D2DPrint"><Rcn>204725</Rcn><Nid>16272</Nid><HI>The Provost, Fellows, Foundation Scholars &amp; The Other Members Of Board Of The College Of The Holy &amp; Undivided Trinity Of Queen Elizabeth Near Dublin, Ireland</HI><Name>3D Printing of Novel 2D Nanomaterials: Adding Advanced 2D Functionalities to Revolutionary Tailored 3D Manufacturing</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), ERC-2015-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>My vision is to establish, within the framework of an ERC CoG, a multidisciplinary group which will work in concert towards pioneering the integration of novel 2-Dimensional nanomaterials with novel additive fabrication techniques to develop a unique class of energy storage devices.

Batteries and supercapacitors are two very complementary types of energy storage devices. Batteries store much higher energy densities; supercapacitors, on the other hand, hold one tenth of the electricity per unit of volume or weight as compared to batteries but can achieve much higher power densities. Technology is currently striving to improve the power density of batteries and the energy density of supercapacitors. To do so it is imperative to develop new materials, chemistries and manufacturing strategies.
3D2DPrint aims to develop micro-energy devices (both supercapacitors and batteries), technologies particularly relevant in the context of the emergent industry of micro-electro-mechanical systems and constantly downsized electronics. We plan to use novel two-dimensional (2D) nanomaterials obtained by liquid-phase exfoliation. This method offers a new, economic and easy way to prepare ink of a variety of 2D systems, allowing to produce wide device performance window through elegant and simple constituent control at the point of fabrication. 3D2DPrint will use our expertise and know-how to allow development of advanced AM methods to integrate dissimilar nanomaterial blends and/or &#8220;hybrids&#8221; into fully embedded 3D printed energy storage devices, with the ultimate objective to realise a range of products that contain the above described nanomaterials subcomponent devices, electrical connections and traditional micro-fabricated subcomponents (if needed) ideally using a single tool.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>2,499,942</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2016-10-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2021-09-30</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="3DSPIN"><Rcn>194514</Rcn><Nid>13977</Nid><HI>Universita Degli Studi Di Pavia, Italy</HI><Name>3-Dimensional Maps of the Spinning Nucleon</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), ERC-2014-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>How does the inside of the proton look like? What generates its spin? 3DSPIN will deliver essential information to answer these questions at the frontier of subnuclear physics.
At present, we have detailed maps of the distribution of quarks and gluons in the nucleon in 1D (as a function of their momentum in a single direction). We also know that quark spins account for only about 1/3 of the spin of the nucleon.
3DSPIN will lead the way into a new stage of nucleon mapping, explore the distribution of quarks in full 3D momentum space and obtain unprecedented information on orbital angular momentum. 
Goals
1. extract from experimental data the 3D distribution of quarks (in momentum space), as described by Transverse-Momentum Distributions (TMDs);
2. obtain from TMDs information on quark Orbital Angular Momentum (OAM).
Methodology
3DSPIN will implement state-of-the-art fitting procedures to analyze relevant experimental data and extract quark TMDs, similarly to global fits of standard parton distribution functions. Information about quark angular momentum will be obtained through assumptions based on theoretical considerations. The next five years represent an ideal time window to accomplish our goals, thanks to the wealth of expected data from deep-inelastic scattering experiments (COMPASS, Jefferson Lab), hadronic colliders (Fermilab, BNL, LHC), and electron-positron colliders (BELLE, BABAR). The PI has a strong reputation in this field. The group will operate in partnership with the Italian National Institute of Nuclear Physics and in close interaction with leading experts and experimental collaborations worldwide.
Impact
Mapping the 3D structure of chemical compounds has revolutionized chemistry. Similarly, mapping the 3D structure of the nucleon will have a deep impact on our understanding of the fundamental constituents of matter. We will open new perspectives on the dynamics of quarks and gluons and sharpen our view of high-energy processes involving nucleons.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding /></Project><Project acronym="3MC"><Rcn>194553</Rcn><Nid>13938</Nid><HI>Universiteit Utrecht, Netherlands</HI><Name>3D Model Catalysts to explore new routes to sustainable fuels</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), ERC-2014-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>Currently fuels, plastics, and drugs are predominantly manufactured from oil. A transition towards renewable resources critically depends on new catalysts, for instance to convert small molecules (such as solar or biomass derived hydrogen, carbon monoxide, water and carbon dioxide) into more complex ones (such as oxygenates, containing oxygen atoms in their structure). Catalyst development now often depends on trial and error rather than rational design, as the heterogeneity of these composite systems hampers detailed understanding of the role of each of the components.  

I propose 3D model catalysts as a novel enabling tool to overcome this problem. Their well-defined nature allows unprecedented precision in the variation of structural parameters (morphology, spatial distribution) of the individual components, while at the same time they mimic real catalysts closely enough to allow testing under industrially relevant conditions. Using this approach I will address fundamental questions, such as:
* What are the mechanisms (structural, electronic, chemical) by which non-metal promoters influence the functionality of copper-based catalysts?
* Which nanoalloys can be formed, how does their composition influence the surface active sites and catalytic functionality under reaction conditions?
* Which size and interface effects occur, and how can we use them to tune the actitivity and selectivity towards desired products?

Our 3D model catalysts will be assembled from ordered mesoporous silica and carbon support materials and Cu-based promoted and bimetallic nanoparticles. The combination with high resolution characterization and testing under realistic conditions allows detailed insight into the role of the different components; critical for the rational design of novel catalysts for a future more sustainable production of chemicals and fuels from renewable resources.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding /></Project><Project acronym="9 SALT"><Rcn>196865</Rcn><Nid>13797</Nid><HI>Universitat Wien, Austria</HI><Name>Reassessing Ninth Century Philosophy. A Synchronic Approach to the Logical Traditions</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), ERC-2014-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>This project aims at a better understanding of the philosophical richness of ninth century thought using the unprecedented and highly innovative method of the synchronic approach. The hypothesis directing this synchronic approach is that studying together in parallel the four main philosophical traditions of the century &#8211; i.e. Latin, Greek, Syriac and Arabic &#8211; will bring results that the traditional enquiry limited to one tradition alone can never reach. This implies pioneering a new methodology to overcome the compartmentalization of research which prevails nowadays. Using this method is only possible because the four conditions of applicability &#8211; comparable intellectual environment, common text corpus, similar methodological perspective, commensurable problems &#8211; are fulfilled. The ninth century, a time of cultural renewal in the Carolingian, Byzantine and Abbasid empires, possesses the remarkable characteristic &#8211; which ensures commensurability &#8211; that the same texts, namely the writings of Aristotelian logic (mainly Porphyry&#8217;s Isagoge and Aristotle&#8217;s Categories) were read and commented upon in Latin, Greek, Syriac and Arabic alike. 
Logic is fundamental to philosophical enquiry. The contested question is the human capacity to rationalise, analyse and describe the sensible reality, to understand the ontological structure of the world, and to define the types of entities which exist. The use of this unprecedented synchronic approach will allow us a deeper understanding of the positions, a clear identification of the a priori postulates of the philosophical debates, and a critical evaluation of the arguments used. It provides a unique opportunity to compare the different traditions and highlight the heritage which is common, to stress the specificities of each tradition when tackling philosophical issues and to discover the doctrinal results triggered by their mutual interactions, be they constructive (scholarly exchanges) or polemic (religious controversies).</Summary><Max_ERC_funding /></Project><Project acronym="A-BINGOS"><Rcn>185648</Rcn><Nid>12022</Nid><HI>Foundation For Research And Technology Hellas, Greece</HI><Name>Accreting binary populations in Nearby Galaxies: Observations and Simulations</Name><PI>Andreas Zezas</PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), PE9, ERC-2013-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>"High-energy observations of our Galaxy offer a good, albeit not complete, picture of the X-ray source populations, in particular the accreting binary sources. Recent ability to study accreting binaries in nearby galaxies has shown that we would be short-sighted if we restricted ourselves to our Galaxy or to a few nearby ones. I propose an ambitious project that involves a comprehensive study of all the galaxies within 10 Mpc for which we can study in detail their X-ray sources and stellar populations. The study will combine data from a unique suite of observatories (Chandra, XMM-Newton, HST, Spitzer) with state-of-the-art theoretical modelling of binary systems. I propose a novel approach that links the accreting binary populations to their parent stellar populations and surpasses any current studies of X-ray binary populations, both in scale and in scope, by: (a) combining methods and results from several different areas of astrophysics (compact objects, binary systems, stellar populations, galaxy evolution); (b) using data from almost the whole electromagnetic spectrum (infrared to X-ray bands); (c) identifying and studying the different sub-populations of accreting binaries; and (d) performing direct comparison between observations and theoretical predictions, over a broad parameter space. The project: (a) will answer the long-standing question of the formation efficiency of accreting binaries in different environments; and (b) will constrain their evolutionary paths. As by-products the project will provide eagerly awaited input to the fields of gravitational-wave sources, &#947;-ray bursts, and X-ray emitting galaxies at cosmological distances and it will produce a heritage multi-wavelength dataset and library of models for future studies of galaxies and accreting binaries."</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,242,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2014-04-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2019-03-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="A-DIET"><Rcn>196851</Rcn><Nid>13810</Nid><HI>University College Dublin, National University Of Ireland, Dublin, Ireland</HI><Name>Metabolomics based biomarkers of dietary intake- new tools for nutrition research</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Consolidator Grants (CoG), ERC-2014-CoG</Call_Details><Summary>In todays advanced technological world, we can track the exact movement of individuals, analyse their genetic makeup and predict predisposition to certain diseases. However, we are unable to accurately assess an individual&#8217;s dietary intake. This is without a doubt one of the main stumbling blocks in assessing the link between diet and disease/health. The present proposal (A-DIET) will address this issue with the overarching objective to develop novel strategies for assessment of dietary intake.
Using approaches to (1) identify biomarkers of specific foods (2) classify people into dietary patterns (nutritypes) and (3) develop a tool for integration of dietary and biomarker data, A-DIET has the potential to dramatically enhance our ability to accurately assess dietary intake. The ultimate output from A-DIET will be a dietary assessment tool which can be used to obtain an accurate assessment of dietary intake by combining dietary and biomarker data which in turn will allow investigations into relationships between diet, health and disease. New biomarkers of specific foods will be identified and validated using intervention studies and metabolomic analyses. Methods will be developed to classify individuals into dietary patterns based on biomarker/metabolomic profiles thus demonstrating the novel concept of nutritypes. Strategies for integration of dietary and biomarker data will be developed and translated into a tool that will be made available to the wider scientific community.
Advances made in A-DIET will enable nutrition epidemiologist&#8217;s to properly examine the relationship between diet and disease and develop clear public health messages with regard to diet and health. Additionally results from A-DIET will allow researchers to accurately assess people&#8217;s diet and implement health promotion strategies and enable dieticians in a clinical environment to assess compliance to therapeutic diets such as adherence to a high fibre diet or a gluten free diet.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,995,548</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2015-08-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2020-07-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2-NanoSi"><Rcn>196369</Rcn><Nid>13899</Nid><HI>Fundacio Privada Institut Catala D'investigacio Quimica, Spain</HI><Name>Ratiometric FRET Based Nanosensors for Trypsin Related Human Recessive Diseases</Name><PI>Alice Jenkins</PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2014-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>The project aims to create a demo system for cost effective, non-invasive device for rapid detection of cystic fibrosis in humans.
The detection of human recessive diseases has been dominated by the use of fluorescent biomarkers, based on organic dyes, helping researchers to study and analyse gene expression, cell cycle, and enzymatic activity. Among several proteolytic enzymes, trypsin has attracted much attention, as it is a target in the study of various important human recessive diseases including, for example, cystic fibrosis (CF).
We present herein two colour encoded silica nanospheres (2nanoSi) for the fluorescence quantitative ratiometric determination of cystic in humans. Current detection technologies for cystic fibrosis diagnosis are slow, costly and suffer from false positives. The 2nanoSi proved to be a fast (minutes), a single-step and with two times higher sensitivity than the state-of-the-art biomarkers based sensors for cystic fibrosis, allowing the quantification of trypsin concentrations in a wide range (25-350 &#956;g/L). Moreover, our approach can be used from the 4th day of life when the trypsin concentration is already the same as in adults. Furthermore, as trypsin is directly related to the development of cystic fibrosis (CF), different human phenotypes, i.e. normal (160-340 &#956;g/L), CF homozygotic (0-90 &#956;g/L), and CF heterozygotic (91-349 &#956;g/L), respectively, can be determined using our 2nanoSi nanospheres. We anticipate the 2nanoSi system to be a starting point for non-invasive, easy-to-use and cost effective ratiometric fluorescence biomarker for recessive genetic diseases alike human cystic fibrosis.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>150,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2015-04-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2016-03-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="1st-principles-discs"><Rcn>106530</Rcn><Nid>10913</Nid><HI>Kobenhavns Universitet, Denmark</HI><Name>A First Principles Approach to Accretion Discs</Name><PI>Martin Elias Pessah</PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), PE9, ERC-2012-StG</Call_Details><Summary>Most celestial bodies, from planets, to stars, to black holes; gain mass during their lives by means of an accretion disc. Understanding the physical processes that determine the rate at which matter accretes and energy is radiated in these discs is vital for unraveling the formation, evolution, and fate of almost every type of object in the Universe. Despite the fact that magnetic fields have been known to be crucial in accretion discs since the early 90&#8217;s, the majority of astrophysical questions that depend on the details of how disc accretion proceeds are still being addressed using the &#8220;standard&#8221; accretion disc model (developed in the early 70&#8217;s), where magnetic fields do not play an explicit role. This has prevented us from fully exploring the astrophysical consequences and observational signatures of realistic accretion disc models, leading to a profound disconnect between observations (usually interpreted with the standard paradigm) and modern accretion disc theory and numerical simulations (where magnetic turbulence is crucial). The goal of this proposal is to use several complementary approaches in order to finally move beyond the standard paradigm. This program has two main objectives: 1) Develop the theoretical framework to incorporate magnetic fields, and the ensuing turbulence, into self-consistent accretion disc models, and investigate their observational implications. 2) Investigate transport and radiative processes in collision-less disc regions, where non-thermal radiation originates, by employing a kinetic particle description of the plasma. In order to achieve these goals, we will use, and build upon, state-of-the-art magnetohydrodynamic and particle-in-cell codes in conjunction with theoretical modeling. This framework will make it possible to address fundamental questions on stellar and planet formation, binary systems with a compact object, and supermassive black hole feedback in a way that has no counterpart within the standard paradigm.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,793,697</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2013-02-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2018-01-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2-3-AUT"><Rcn>92475</Rcn><Nid>9838</Nid><HI>Kobenhavns Universitet, Denmark</HI><Name>"Surfaces, 3-manifolds and automorphism groups"</Name><PI>Nathalie Wahl</PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), PE1, ERC-2009-StG</Call_Details><Summary>"The scientific goal of the proposal is to answer central questions related to diffeomorphism groups of manifolds of dimension 2 and 3, and to their deformation invariant analogs, the mapping class groups. While the classification of surfaces has been known for more than a century, their automorphism groups have yet to be fully understood. Even less is known about diffeomorphisms of 3-manifolds despite much interest, and the objects here have only been classified recently, by the breakthrough work of Perelman on the Poincar\'e and geometrization conjectures. In dimension 2, I will focus on the relationship between mapping class groups and topological conformal field theories, with applications to Hochschild homology. In dimension 3, I propose to compute the stable homology of classifying spaces of diffeomorphism groups and mapping class groups, as well as study the homotopy type of the space of diffeomorphisms. I propose moreover to establish homological stability theorems in the wider context of automorphism groups and more general families of groups. The project combines breakthrough methods from homotopy theory with methods from differential and geometric topology. The research team will consist of 3 PhD students, and 4 postdocs, which I will lead."</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>724,992</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2009-11-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2014-10-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2-HIT"><Rcn>87935</Rcn><Nid>9711</Nid><HI>Fundacio Centre De Regulacio Genomica, Spain</HI><Name>Genetic interaction networks: From C. elegans to human disease</Name><PI>Ben Lehner</PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), LS2, ERC-2007-StG</Call_Details><Summary>"Most hereditary diseases in humans are genetically complex, resulting from combinations of mutations in multiple genes. However synthetic interactions between genes are very difficult to identify in population studies because of a lack of statistical power and we fundamentally do not understand how mutations interact to produce phenotypes. C. elegans is a unique animal in which genetic interactions can be rapidly identified in vivo using RNA interference, and we recently used this system to construct the first genetic interaction network for any animal, focused on signal transduction genes. The first objective of this proposal is to extend this work and map a comprehensive genetic interaction network for this model metazoan. This project will provide the first insights into the global properties of animal genetic interaction networks, and a comprehensive view of the functional relationships between genes in an animal. The second objective of the proposal is to use C. elegans to develop and validate experimentally integrated gene networks that connect genes to phenotypes and predict genetic interactions on a genome-wide scale. The methods that we develop and validate in C. elegans will then be applied to predict phenotypes and interactions for human genes. The final objective is to dissect the molecular mechanisms underlying genetic interactions, and to understand how these interactions evolve. The combined aim of these three objectives is to generate a framework for understanding and predicting how mutations interact to produce phenotypes, including in human disease."</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,100,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2008-09-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2014-04-30</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="20SComplexity"><Rcn>193418</Rcn><Nid>14273</Nid><HI>Weizmann Institute Of Science, Israel</HI><Name>An integrative approach to uncover the multilevel regulation of 20S proteasome degradation</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), ERC-2014-STG</Call_Details><Summary>For many years, the ubiquitin-26S proteasome degradation pathway was considered the primary route for proteasomal degradation. However, it is now becoming clear that proteins can also be targeted for degradation by a ubiquitin-independent mechanism mediated by the core 20S proteasome itself. Although initially believed to be limited to rare exceptions, degradation by the 20S proteasome is now understood to have a wide range of substrates, many of which are key regulatory proteins. Despite its importance, little is known about the mechanisms that control 20S proteasomal degradation, unlike the extensive knowledge acquired over the years concerning degradation by the 26S proteasome. Our overall aim is to reveal the multiple regulatory levels that coordinate the 20S proteasome degradation route.
To achieve this goal we will carry out a comprehensive research program characterizing three distinct levels of 20S proteasome regulation:
Intra-molecular regulation- Revealing the intrinsic molecular switch that activates the latent 20S proteasome.
Inter-molecular regulation- Identifying novel proteins that bind the 20S proteasome to regulate its activity and characterizing their mechanism of function.
Cellular regulatory networks- Unraveling the cellular cues and multiple pathways that influence 20S proteasome activity using a novel systematic and unbiased screening approach.
Our experimental strategy involves the combination of biochemical approaches with native mass spectrometry, cross-linking and fluorescence measurements, complemented by cell biology analyses and high-throughput screening. Such a multidisciplinary approach, integrating in vitro and in vivo findings, will likely provide the much needed knowledge on the 20S proteasome degradation route. When completed, we anticipate that this work will be part of a new paradigm &#8211; no longer perceiving the 20S proteasome mediated degradation as a simple and passive event but rather a tightly regulated and coordinated process.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding /></Project><Project acronym="2DMATER"><Rcn>104627</Rcn><Nid>10564</Nid><HI>Technische Universitaet Dresden, Germany</HI><Name>Controlled Synthesis of Two-Dimensional Nanomaterials for Energy Storage and Conversion</Name><PI>Xinliang Feng</PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), PE5, ERC-2012-StG</Call_Details><Summary>"Two-dimensional (2D) nanosheets, which possess a high degree of anisotropy with nanoscale thickness and infinite length in other dimensions, hold enormous promise as a novel class of ultrathin 2D nanomaterials with various unique functionalities and properties, and exhibit great potential in energy storage and conversion systems that are substantially different from their respective 3D bulk forms. Here I propose a strategy for the synthesis and processing of various 2D nanosheets across a broad range of inorganic, organic and polymeric materials with molecular-level or thin thickness through both the top-down exfoliation of layered materials and the bottom-up assembly of available molecular building blocks. Further, I aim to develop the synthesis of various 2D-nanosheet based composite materials with thickness of less than 100 nm and the assembly of 2D nanosheets into novel hierarchal superstrucutures (like aerogels, spheres, porous particles, nanotubes, multi-layer films). The structural features of these 2D nanomaterials will be controllably tailored by both the used layered precursors and processing methodologies. The consequence is that I will apply and combine defined functional components as well as assembly protocols to create novel 2D nanomaterials for specific purposes in energy storage and conversion systems. Their unique characters will include the good electrical conductivity, excellent mechanical flexibility, high surface area, high chemical stability, fast electron transport and ion diffusion etc. Applications will be mainly demonstrated for the construction of lithium ion batteries (anode and cathode), supercapacitors (symmetric and asymmetric) and fuel cells. As the key achievements, I expect to establish the delineation of reliable structure-property relationships and improved device performance of 2D nanomaterials."</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,500,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2012-09-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2017-08-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2DNanoCaps"><Rcn>100397</Rcn><Nid>12132</Nid><HI>The Provost, Fellows, Foundation Scholars &amp; The Other Members Of Board Of The College Of The Holy &amp; Undivided Trinity Of Queen Elizabeth Near Dublin, Ireland</HI><Name>Next Generation of 2D-Nanomaterials: Enabling Supercapacitor Development</Name><PI>Valeria Nicolosi</PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), PE8, ERC-2011-StG</Call_Details><Summary>Climate change and the decreasing availability of fossil fuels require society to move towards sustainable and renewable resources. 2DNanoCaps will focus on electrochemical energy storage, specifically supercapacitors. In terms of performance supercapacitors fill up the gap between batteries and the classical capacitors. Whereas batteries possess a high energy density but low power density, supercapacitors possess high power density but low energy density. Efforts are currently dedicated to move supercapacitors towards high energy density and high power density performance. Improvements have been achieved in the last few years due to the use of new electrode nanomaterials and the design of new hybrid faradic/capacitive systems. We recognize, however, that we are reaching a newer limit beyond which we will only see small incremental improvements. The main reason for this being the intrinsic difficulty in handling and processing materials at the nano-scale and the lack of communication across different scientific disciplines. I plan to use a multidisciplinary approach, where novel nanomaterials, existing knowledge on nano-scale processing and established expertise in device fabrication and testing will be brought together to focus on creating more efficient supercapacitor technologies. 2DNanoCaps will exploit liquid phase exfoliated two-dimensional nanomaterials such as transition metal oxides, layered metal chalcogenides and graphene as electrode materials. Electrodes will be ultra-thin (capacitance and thickness of the electrodes are inversely proportional), conductive, with high dielectric constants. Intercalation of ions between the assembled 2D flakes will be also achievable, providing pseudo-capacitance. The research here proposed will be initially based on fundamental laboratory studies, recognising that this holds the key to achieving step-change in supercapacitors, but also includes scaling-up and hybridisation as final objectives.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,501,296</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2011-10-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2016-09-30</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2DTHERMS"><Rcn>94903</Rcn><Nid>13070</Nid><HI>Universidad De Santiago De Compostela, Spain</HI><Name>Design of new thermoelectric devices based on layered and field modulated nanostructures of strongly correlated electron systems</Name><PI>Jose Francisco Rivadulla Fernandez</PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), PE3, ERC-2010-StG</Call_Details><Summary>Design of new thermoelectric devices based on layered and field modulated nanostructures of strongly correlated electron systems</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,427,190</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2010-11-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2015-10-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2D&#8211;SYNETRA"><Rcn>106908</Rcn><Nid>9737</Nid><HI>Universitaet Hamburg, Germany</HI><Name>Two-dimensional colloidal nanostructures- Synthesis and electrical transport</Name><PI>Christian Klinke</PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), PE4, ERC-2012-StG</Call_Details><Summary>"We propose to develop truly two-dimensional continuous materials and two-dimensional monolayer films composed of individual nanocrystals by the comparatively fast, inexpensive, and scalable colloidal synthesis method. The materials&#8217; properties will be studied in detail, especially regarding their (photo-) electrical transport. This will allow developing new types of device structures, such as Coulomb blockade and field enhancement based transistors.

Recently, we demonstrated the possibility to synthesize in a controlled manner truly two-dimensional colloidal nanostructures. We will investigate their formation mechanism, synthesize further materials as &#8220;nanosheets&#8221;, develop methodologies to tune their geometrical properties, and study their (photo-) electrical properties.

Furthermore, we will use the Langmuir-Blodgett method to deposit highly ordered monolayers of monodisperse nanoparticles. Such structures show interesting transport properties governed by Coulomb blockade effects known from individual nanoparticles. This leads to semiconductor-like behavior in metal nanoparticle films. The understanding of the electric transport in such &#8220;multi-tunnel devices&#8221; is still very limited. Thus, we will investigate this concept in detail and take it to its limits. Beside improvement of quality and exchange of material we will tune the nanoparticles&#8217; size and shape in order to gain a deeper understanding of the electrical properties of supercrystallographic assemblies. Furthermore, we will develop device concepts for diode and transistor structures which take into account the novel properties of the low-dimensional assemblies.

Nanosheets and monolayers of nanoparticles truly follow the principle of building devices by the bottom-up approach and allow electric transport measurements in a 2D regime. Highly ordered nanomaterial systems possess easy and reliably to manipulate electronic properties what make them interesting for future (inexpensive) electronic devices."</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,497,200</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2013-02-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2018-01-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2F4BIODYN"><Rcn>100953</Rcn><Nid>10781</Nid><HI>Centre National De La Recherche Scientifique, France</HI><Name>Two-Field Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy for the Exploration of Biomolecular Dynamics</Name><PI>Fabien Ferrage</PI><Call_Details>Starting Grant (StG), PE4, ERC-2011-StG</Call_Details><Summary>The paradigm of the structure-function relationship in proteins is outdated. Biological macromolecules and supramolecular assemblies are highly dynamic objects. Evidence that their motions are of utmost importance to their functions is regularly identified. The understanding of the physical chemistry of biological processes at an atomic level has to rely not only on the description of structure but also on the characterization of molecular motions.
The investigation of protein motions will be undertaken with a very innovative methodological approach in nuclear magnetic resonance relaxation. In order to widen the ranges of frequencies at which local motions in proteins are probed, we will first use and develop new techniques for a prototype shuttle system for the measurement of relaxation at low fields on a high-field NMR spectrometer. Second, we will develop a novel system: a set of low-field NMR spectrometers designed as accessories for high-field spectrometers. Used in conjunction with the shuttle, this system will offer (i) the sensitivity and resolution (i.e. atomic level information) of a high-field spectrometer (ii) the access to low fields of a relaxometer and (iii) the ability to measure a wide variety of relaxation rates with high accuracy. This system will benefit from the latest technology in homogeneous permanent magnet development to allow a control of spin systems identical to that of a high-resolution probe. This new apparatus will open the way to the use of NMR relaxation at low fields for the refinement of protein motions at an atomic scale.
Applications of this novel approach will focus on the bright side of protein dynamics: (i) the largely unexplored dynamics of intrinsically disordered proteins, and (ii) domain motions in large proteins. In both cases, we will investigate a series of diverse protein systems with implications in development, cancer and immunity.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>1,462,080</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2012-01-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2017-12-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2-NanoSi"><Rcn>196369</Rcn><Nid>13899</Nid><HI>Fundacio Privada Institut Catala D'investigacio Quimica, Spain</HI><Name>Ratiometric FRET Based Nanosensors for Trypsin Related Human Recessive Diseases</Name><PI>Alice Jenkins</PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2014-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>The project aims to create a demo system for cost effective, non-invasive device for rapid detection of cystic fibrosis in humans.
The detection of human recessive diseases has been dominated by the use of fluorescent biomarkers, based on organic dyes, helping researchers to study and analyse gene expression, cell cycle, and enzymatic activity. Among several proteolytic enzymes, trypsin has attracted much attention, as it is a target in the study of various important human recessive diseases including, for example, cystic fibrosis (CF).
We present herein two colour encoded silica nanospheres (2nanoSi) for the fluorescence quantitative ratiometric determination of cystic in humans. Current detection technologies for cystic fibrosis diagnosis are slow, costly and suffer from false positives. The 2nanoSi proved to be a fast (minutes), a single-step and with two times higher sensitivity than the state-of-the-art biomarkers based sensors for cystic fibrosis, allowing the quantification of trypsin concentrations in a wide range (25-350 &#956;g/L). Moreover, our approach can be used from the 4th day of life when the trypsin concentration is already the same as in adults. Furthermore, as trypsin is directly related to the development of cystic fibrosis (CF), different human phenotypes, i.e. normal (160-340 &#956;g/L), CF homozygotic (0-90 &#956;g/L), and CF heterozygotic (91-349 &#956;g/L), respectively, can be determined using our 2nanoSi nanospheres. We anticipate the 2nanoSi system to be a starting point for non-invasive, easy-to-use and cost effective ratiometric fluorescence biomarker for recessive genetic diseases alike human cystic fibrosis.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>150,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2015-04-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2016-03-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2D-Ink"><Rcn>196353</Rcn><Nid>13914</Nid><HI>The Provost, Fellows, Foundation Scholars &amp; The Other Members Of Board Of The College Of The Holy &amp; Undivided Trinity Of Queen Elizabeth Near Dublin, Ireland</HI><Name>Ink-Jet printed supercapacitors based on 2D nanomaterials.</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2014-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>This proposal will determine the technical-economic viability of scaling-up ultra-thin, ink-jet printed films based on liquid-phase exfoliated single atomic layers of a range of nanomaterials. The PI has developed methods to produce in liquid nanosheets of a range of layered materials such as graphene, transition metal oxides, etc. These 2D-materials have immediate and far-reaching potential in several high-impact technological applications such as microelectronics, composites and energy harvesting and storage.  2DNanoCaps (ERC ref: 278516) has demonstrated that lab-scale ultra-thin graphene-based supercapacitor electrodes result in unusually high-power and extremely long device life-time (100% capacitance retention for 5000 charge-discharge cycles at the high power scan rate of 10,000 mV/s). This performance is an order of magnitude better than similar systems produced with conventional methods which cause materials restacking and aggregation. A following ERC PoC grant (2D-USD, Project-Number 620189) is currently focussed on up-scaling the production of thin-films deposition methods based on ultrasonic spray for the production of large-area electrodes for supercapacitors applications. In this proposal we want to explore the new concept of manufacturing conductive, robust, thin, easily assembled electrode and solid electrolytes to realize highly-flexible and all-solid-state supercapacitors by ink-jet printing. This opportunity is particularly relevant to the electronics and portable-device industry and offers the possibility to solve flammability issues, maintaining light weight, flexibility, transparency and portability. In order to do so it will be imperative to develop ink-jet printing methods and techniques. We believe our combination of unique materials and cost-effective, robust and production-scalable process of ultra- thin ink-jet printing will enable us to compete for significant global market opportunities in the energy-storage space.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>149,774</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2015-04-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2016-09-30</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2D-USD"><Rcn>111558</Rcn><Nid>10068</Nid><HI>The Provost Fellows &amp; Scholars Of The College Of The Holy And Undivided Trinity Of Queen Elizabeth Near Dublin, Ireland</HI><Name>Ultrasonic Spray Deposition: Enabling new 2D based technologies</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2013-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>"This proposal will determine the technical and economic viability of scaling up ultra-thin film deposition processes for exfoliated single atomic layers.
The PI has developed methods to produce exfoliated nanosheets from a range of layered materials such as graphene, transition metal chalcogenides and transition metal oxides. These 2D materials have immediate and far-reaching potential in several high-impact technological applications such as microelectronics, composites and energy harvesting and storage.
2DNanoCaps (ERC ref: 278516) has already demonstrated that lab-scale ultra-thin graphene-based supercapacitor electrodes for energy storage result in unusually high power performance and extremely long device life-time (100% capacitance retention for 5000 charge-discharge cycles at the high power scan rate of 10,000 mV/s). This performance is remarkable- an order of magnitude better than similar systems produced with more conventional methods, which cause materials restacking and aggregation. 2D nanosheets also offer the chance of exploring the unique possibility of manufacturing conductive, robust, thin, easily assembled electrode and solid electrolytes to realize highly flexible and all-solid-state supercapacitors. This opportunity is particularly relevant from the industrial point of view especially in relation to the flammability issues of the electrolytes used for commercial energy storage devices at present.
In order to develop and exploit any of the applications listed above, it will be imperative to develop deposition methods and techniques capable of obtaining industrial-scale &#8220;sheet-like&#8221; coverage, where flake re-aggregation is avoided.
We believe our combination of unique material properties and cost effective, robust and production-scalable process of ultra-thin deposition will enable us to compete for significant global market opportunities in the energy-storage space"</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>148,021</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2014-01-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2014-12-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2DIR SPECTROMETER"><Rcn>110825</Rcn><Nid>10168</Nid><HI>Imperial College Of Science, Technology And Medicine, United Kingdom</HI><Name>A step-change in sensitivity for two dimensional laser infrared spectroscopy</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2013-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>"Here, we propose a novel design for a significantly improved detector for the emerging field of coherent two-dimension infrared (2DIR) spectroscopy, which is an optical analog of Nuclear Magnetic Resonance spectroscopy (NMR). 2DIR is a cutting edge technique which is rapidly growing and has applications in subjects as diverse as energy sciences, biophysics, biomedical research and physical chemistry. Currently, the single most important technical problem that is generally agreed to limit applications of the methodology is the sensitivity with which the signals are measured. Having worked on multiple stabilisation techniques during the ERC funded research it was realised that a straightforward design alteration of the infrared detector will improve the sensitivity very significantly, theoretically by more than one order of magnitude. Here, the technical principles are explained, and a plan for commercialising the instrument in collaboration with the current market leader - Infrared System Development Corp. (ISDC) -. We apply for funding to develop the prototype."</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>149,999</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2013-11-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2014-10-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="2MoveMate4Melanoma"><Rcn>203176</Rcn><Nid>15816</Nid><HI>Stichting Het Nederlands Kanker Instituut-Antoni Van Leeuwenhoek Ziekenhuis, Netherlands</HI><Name>A treatment for BRAF inhibitor resistant melanoma</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2015-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>Some 50% of human melanoma tumors have activating mutations in the BRAF gene. BRAF inhibitor drugs given either alone or in combination with MEK inhibitors have improved progression-free and overall survival in patients with BRAF mutant metastatic melanoma. However, drug resistance invariably limits the duration of clinical benefit of such treatments and is almost always associated with re-activation of signaling through the MAP kinase pathway in the presence of drug due to secondary mutations in the pathway. This highlights the urgent need to develop strategies to treat melanomas that have developed resistance to BRAF and/or MEK inhibitors. 
As part of an ERC advanced grant, my laboratory has shown that BRAF inhibitor withdrawal in melanomas that have developed resistance to BRAF inhibitors leads to a transient growth arrest that is the consequence of temporary hyperactivation of signaling through the MAP kinase pathway, explaining the so called &#8220;drug holiday effect&#8221;. We have also found that subsequent treatment of such BRAF inhibitor resistant melanomas with Histone DeACetylase inhibitor drugs (HDACi) leads to persistent hyperactivation of MAP kinase signaling, causing both chronic proliferation arrest and cell death, ultimately leading to complete regression of BRAF-inhibitor resistant melanomas in mice. 
We propose here to perform a proof of concept study in at least 10 evaluable melanoma patients that, after proven initial tumor response, have developed resistance to BRAF inhibitors to validate that subsequent treatment of such patients with an HDACi drug will result in durable responses. Translational studies on tumor biopsies taken before, during and after HDACi treatment will be performed to study the cellular effects of HDACi treatment. Our goal is to provide initial proof of concept in patients for use of this sequential BRAFi-HDACi therapy as the treatment of choice for the some 40,000 BRAF mutant melanomas that are diagnosed in the EU annually.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>149,750</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2016-05-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2017-10-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="3D-COUNT"><Rcn>199129</Rcn><Nid>15258</Nid><HI>Universita Degli Studi Di Roma La Sapienza, Italy</HI><Name>3D-Integrated single photon detector</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2015-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>Photonics, in recognition of its strategic significance and pervasiveness throughout many industrial sectors, has been identified as one of the Key Enabling Technologies for Europe. Photonics in combination with quantum information science has great potential to facilitate, transform and innovate future technologies for the better. The Proof of Concept (PoC) project intends to contribute to this by developing and testing a communication platform prototype, comprised of single photon detectors, which are efficiently coupled to single mode fibers using an innovative laser written device. This enables the integration of single photon detectors on innovative glass waveguides. These glass integrated photonic circuits offer excellent specifics for on-chip quantum optics implementations in terms of scattering losses, offering flexibility of the waveguide geometry and ensuring high coupling efficiency with optical fibers.
The device developed and tested in the PoC, directly addresses a market need for an integrated and efficient on-chip communication systems. Current available systems have limitations involving high costs, complex production, and inefficient coupling of detectors to optical fibers. The proposed platform will offer 1.) a simplified production process, 2.) high optical fiber coupling efficiency 3.) improved performance levels, 4.) high cost efficiency, and 5.) compactness. Such systems can be applied in a wide range of communication and non-communication applications, such as free-space optical communication, quantum communication, quantum cryptography, DNA sequencing, single molecule detection and material analysis. Moreover, the future commercialisation of quantum computing is expected to create a vast demand for these communication systems. 
In addition to the technology PoC, the project carries out IPR strategy considerations through patenting actions, determines the market potential, seeks market feedback, and plans for post-PoC commercialisation paths.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>150,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2016-02-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2017-07-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="3DV"><Rcn>103796</Rcn><Nid>10905</Nid><HI>Universita Degli Studi Di Parma, Italy</HI><Name>Sensor for 3D Vision</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2011-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>"A low-cost sensor able to perceive 3D information would be a breakthrough for a number of applications. Automotive applications would benefit from a low-cost obstacle detector to increase road safety; agricultural vehicles would be able to sense the environment and perform precise (and even autonomous) maneuvers improving their effectiveness; efficient sensing would be a key also to future building automation: elevators doors would close just after boarding and keep open when detecting people's intention to enter, automatic doors would not open when individuals would move in their sensed area but without the intention to cross the door. Even the entertainment industry, which lately invested massively on innovative and interactive sensors, would benefit from precise 3D sensors working even outdoor or in combination with multiple identical sensors.

This proposal is aimed at preparing an engineered version of the current stereo-based system developed for vehicles within the OFAV ERC-funded Advanced Grant and currently under test in many other application domains. It is based on two microcameras and a smart software reconstructing the 3D environment; the software will be ported on a low-cost FPGA+DSP integrated into the sensor box, providing a small and light passive sensor for a variety of applications that nowadays either use other technologies (laser based) or are not able to reach the performance provided by this sensor (e.g. IR-based elevators' door control which is not working in highly illuminated sites and covers only smaller areas).

The algorithm which is now working on a PC-based platform is owned by the team working for the OFAV  Project and delivers superb results in terms of accuracy. This proposal is intended to provide resources to implement this solution in hardware and produce a low-cost, small-sized, and high performance sensor to be used in a very wide range of applications."</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>148,061</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2012-06-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2013-10-31</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="7TReImHo"><Rcn>109074</Rcn><Nid>9385</Nid><HI>Istituto Europeo Di Oncologia Srl, Italy</HI><Name>7kDa TSLP as a novel type of anti-inflammatory agent to re-establish immune homeostasis</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2012-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>Intestinal homeostasis is a complex event that relies on different interactions between the host and the commensal flora, also called microbiota. The microbiota is a source of gene products that are required for several functions linked to digestion and energy harvest, thus it has to be tolerated, but at the same time controlled. We have shown that the capacity to tolerate the microbiota is linked to a close interaction between epithelial cells, that are the first line of defence against luminal microorganisms, and specialized immune cells called dendritic cells, that acquire a tolerogenic phenotype and drive the development of T regulatory cells, capable to control the development of inflammatory responses to bacteria. We have identified several effectors mediating this control and focused on a cytokine called thymic stromal lymphopoietin (TSLP) that is released constitutively by epithelial cells and is strongly downregulated in inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). By contrast, in other inflammatory disorders like allergy or asthma, TSLP has been shown to be upregulated and to mediate disease.
This apparent controversy is solved when considering that TSLP comes in two different isoforms: a short (sTSLP) and a long (lTSLP). sTSLP has been completely neglected in the literature as most of the reagents do not distinguish it from lTSLP. Within the ERC project Dendroworld, we have generated all the tools to study the function of these two isoforms. We discovered that in IBD there is an inverse correlation between sTSLP and lTSLP. lTSLP is drastically upregulated by recruited immune cells, while sTSLP is downregulated in epithelial cells. Hence, we hypothesized and confirmed that the two isoforms had different activities, with the sTSLP being anti-inflammatory and lTSLP being inflammatory.
In this POC we propose scientific and commercialization activities to bring sTSLP to the market as a new class of anti-inflammatory drugs capable of re-establishing immune homeostasis.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>146,917</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2013-07-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2014-06-30</End_date></Duration></Project><Project acronym="A CACTUS"><Rcn>193767</Rcn><Nid>13821</Nid><HI>Universita Degli Studi Di Udine, Italy</HI><Name>Antibody-free method for Counting All Circulating TUmour cellS while maintaining them alive and intact</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2014-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>The problem: Cancer metastases are responsible for 90% of cancer-associated deaths. Circulating tumour cells (CTCs) that enter the blood stream on their way to potential metastatic sites are of obvious interest to evaluate correctly patient treatment and therefore influence outcome. CTCs have been identified in bladder, gastric, prostate, lung, breast and colon cancer. The only FDA approved CTCs detection system is Veridex&#8217; CellSearch, which detects only epithelial cancer cells using antibody labelling. Recent evidence showed that non-epithelial cancer cells, which are not detected by CellSearch, are of critical importance in cancer progression. 

The idea: Our CTC detection method is based, instead of on antibody labelling, on metabolic features of cancer cells, thus providing potential for detecting both epithelial and mesenchymal cancer cells. Cancer cells induce environmental changes; e.g. in aerobic conditions most cancer cells display a high rate of glycolysis with lactate production in the cytosol, known as the Warburg effect.  By separating cells into micro-droplets of pico-liter volume using micro-fluidic water-in-oil emulsions and by characterising the microenvironment surrounding them, CTCs are detected by probing for environmental changes using pH sensitive dyes or enzymatic lactate assays. Our inexpensive diagnostic method provides a way to count and isolate CTCs without any labelling while maintaining cells alive and intact for further studies.

The project: &#8220;A CACTUS&#8221; is meant to assess the feasibility of commercialising the developed method for counting and sorting CTCs and develop a proper commercialisation strategy. The final goal of this project is to develop a proposition package consisting of technical proof of concept, the business proposition and strategy and an IP portfolio and strategy. This information will be presented in an attractive business plan that will be proposed to potential investors.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding /></Project><Project acronym="ACOFORS"><Rcn>196365</Rcn><Nid>13902</Nid><HI>Stichting Vu-Vumc, Netherlands</HI><Name>Launching Acoustic Force Spectroscopy- unlocking the potential of biomolecular bungee jumping</Name><PI> </PI><Call_Details>Proof of Concept (PoC), ERC-2014-PoC</Call_Details><Summary>ACOFORS has been designed with the ultimate goal of preparing commercialisation of Acoustic Force Spectroscopy (AFS). AFS is a completely new and powerful technique for determining biomolecular mechanics and structure of single molecules such as DNA and proteins. These studies are performed on a large scale by biologists and within pharmaceutical companies for e.g. drug discovery and development. Current technologies for force spectroscopy (FS) represent a $50+ million market, but are expensive, require high levels of specialism and are laborious. AFS, invented in the laboratory of Prof. Wuite, is much simpler to use, can be operated in high-throughput mode and can become available at relative low cost. As such, AFS vastly expands the possibilities of FS and makes it available to a much wider community. This makes AFS a very attractive technology for science and business, both from the perspective of the user and of the seller.    
In ACOFORS, a team of scientists and business developers will transform the current prototype in a marketable product, strengthen the intellectual property position, build a solid business case based on an extensive market analysis and take steps towards licensing the technology to industry.</Summary><Max_ERC_funding>150,000</Max_ERC_funding><Duration><Start_date> 2015-07-01, </Start_date><End_date> 2016-06-30</End_date></Duration></Project></PoCProjects>